A Guide to the Publications of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1947-1997
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Separate Publications
  - Verner, Coolie. A Further Checklist of the Separate Editions of Jefferson's Notes on the State of Virginia. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1950. 26 pp. (incl. front cover)., 1950.5
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers. Issued with extra, loose copy of p. 3, "Contents and Hand List for Checking Editions of Jefferson's Notes [1950.5]," containing invitation to owners of the
    "to return the duplicate sheet marked with additional locations to the Secretary of the Bibliographical Society." Responses in
    14 (July 1950), 15 (Nov. 1950), 16 (Feb. 1951), 17 (Mar. 1951), 18 (July 1951).
  - Wright, David McCord. The Economic Library of the President of the Bank of the United States, 1819-1823. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1950. 15, [2] pp., 1950.6
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers. "An address before the Bibiographical Society of the University of Virginia November 7, 1950."
  - Barrett, C. Waller. Henry Adams. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1951. 17 pp., 1951.1
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers, with tape spine. "An address before the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia May 3, 1951."
  - Catlin, Mrs. Randolph [Hannah Hastings White]. The Derrydale Press: Notes from an Informal Talk before the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia / December 13, 1950 / With a Checklist of the Derrydale Books Printed after the Summer of 1937. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1951. 9 pp., 1951.2
  - Fishwick, Marshall W., and William M. Hollis. Preliminary Checklist of Writings about R. E. Lee. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1951. 42 pp. (incl. front cover)., 1951.3
  - Stern, Madeleine B. William Williams: Pioneer Printer of Utica, New York, 1787-1850. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1951. 22 pp., 1951.4
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers. "Paper Read before the Oneida Historical Society of Utica, New York, February 12, 1951."
  - Byrd, Ruth Evelyn. Exhibition Catalogue: Books, Drawings, Prints from the Botanical Collection of Mrs. Roy Arthur Hunt. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1952. 22 pp., 1952.1
    Self paper wrappers. Introduction signed Rachel McMasters Miller Hunt, Pittsburgh, 1952. "Exhibited at the University of Virginia 25 April to 10 June by the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1952." "The printing of this catalogue has been made possible through the generosity of Mr. Linton R. Massey of Keswick. Cover design by Charles W. Smith. Designed and produced by the University of Virginia Press."
  - Harwell, Richard Barksdale. Cornerstones of Confederate Collecting. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1952. 44 pp., 1952.2
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers; a "near-print publication." "The books discussed in this paper were described in a talk by the author to the Caxton Club, Chicago, January 28, 1950. That discussion has been rewritten and extended (though none of the selections has been changed) for presentation here." For second edition see 1953.2. 500 copies.
  - Hooker, Helene Maxwell. The Editing of Recent Historical Papers and Their Value for the Literary Student. Charlottesville: Produced for the English Institute by Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1952. 14 pp., 1952.3
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers; a "near-print publication." "A paper read before the English Institute in September 1951."
  - Mish, Charles C. English Prose Fiction 1600-1640. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1952. v (incl. front cover), 34 pp., 1952.4
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers; a "near-print publication." Part 1 of
    English Prose Fiction, 1600-1700: A Chronological Checklist
    . Corrigendum laid in: "The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia regrets that, through an editorial oversight, the present checklist is not as accurately titled as it should have been. The 1600-1640 list is actually the first section of a chronological overview of the whole seventeenth century's fiction, and will be followed by two more sections, dealing respectively with the periods 1641-1600 [sic] and 1661-1700. A titlepage for the entire list will be provided with the last section." For later edition see 1967.7. 300 copies.
  - Mish, Charles C. English Prose Fiction 1641-1660. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1952. iii (incl. front cover), 21 pp., 1952.5
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers; a "near-print publication." Part 2 of
    . 300 copies.
  - Mish, Charles C. English Prose Fiction 1660-1700. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1952. v, 87 pp., 1952.6
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers. Part 3 of
    . "This third (and last) section of the chronological checklist of English prose fiction in the seventeenth century follows the same plan of procedure as its predecessors.... A title-page to cover the entire checklist has been provided with this section." 300 copies.
  - Mott, Howard S. Collecting Southern Amateur Fiction of the Nineteenth Century. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1952. 14 pp., 1952.7
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers; a "near-print publication." "An address before the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia November 7, 1951."
  - Quenzel, Carrol H. Samuel Snowden, a Founding Father of Printing in Alexandria. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia 1952. 29 pp. (incl. front cover)., 1952.8
  - Spivey, Herman E. Assembling, Arranging, and Publicizing Literary Manuscripts. Charlottesville: Produced for the English Institute by Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1952. 20 pp., 1952.9
  - A Virginia Gentleman's Library as Proposed by Thomas Jefferson to Robert Skipwith in 1771 and Now Assembled in the Brush-Everard House, Williamsburg, Virginia. [Williamsburg, Va.]: Colonial Williamsburg, 1952. 15, [1] pp., 1952.10
    Self paper wrappers. Special issue with colophon on last page: "One hundred and fifty copies have been distributed as a keepsake to those attending the joint meeting of the Bibliographical Society of America and the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia on May 9-10, 1952."
  - [Wyllie, John Cook, ed.] Thomas Jefferson's Prayer Book. [Meriden, Conn.: Meriden Gravure Company, 1952.] [20] pp., 1952.11
    Stiff paper wrappers. Preface signed "J.C.W." "This keepsake is issued by the Meriden Gravure Company for those attending the joint meeting of the Bibliographical Society of America, and the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, held in Charlottesville, Virginia, on May 9-10, 1952 | Design by P. J. Conkwright."
  - Bristol, Roger Pattrell. Maryland Imprints 1801- 1810. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press Press for Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1953. xxviii, 310 pp., 1953.1
    "Three hundred copies of this work have been lithoprinted by Edwards Brothers of Ann Arbor from copy prepared by the author. The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia has acted as agent in financing the publication, but [hardcover] copies may be purchased only from the University of Virginia Press." Addenda by Bristol in
    27 (July 1953), 29 (Oct. 1953), 30 (February 1954), 34 (Oct. 1955).
  - Harwell, Richard Barksdale. Cornerstones of Confederate Collecting. 2nd ed., revised. With facsimiles and an Introduction by Clifford Dowdey. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press for Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1953. iv, 35, [10] pp., 1953.2
    "
    Cornerstones of Confederate Collecting
    has been produced in an edition of five hundred copies at the University of Virginia Press. The machine and hand composition is by Mark Rinker and Walter Collins. The presswork is by J. A. McCrary. The body type is Baskerville, 12 on 13 for the text, with the quotations in 10 point and the notes in 8 point. The handset display type is Lydian. The illustrations are printed by offset from unretouched negatives by Conrad Poluito. The paper is seventy-pound Sulgrave wove." For first edition see 1952.2.
  - Mitchell, Eleanor Drake. A Preliminary Checklist of Tennessee Imprints, 1861-1866. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1953. [1], 98, [1] pp., 1953.3
    Mimeographed; stiff paper wrappers. 300 copies.
  - Pierson, Roscoe M. A Preliminary Checklist of Lexington, Ky., Imprints, 1821-1850. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1953. 155 pp., 1953.4
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers. 300 copies.
  - Aldrich, Ethelyn A. A Directory of the Book Trade in Greenfield, Massachusetts, 1792-1899. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1954. [2], vi, 102, [2] pp., 1954.1
    Stapled gatherings; no covering. "Offset from the author's [typescript] copy by The University of Virginia Press under the supervision of Mark Rinker. Negatives and presswork by Conrad P. Poluito."
  - Graves, Joseph. Victor Hammer: Calligrapher, Punch-Cutter, & Printer. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1954. 12 pp., 1954.2
    Self paper wrappers. "The following was read at the joint meeting of the Bibliographical Society of America and the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia in the McGregor Room of the Alderman Library, Charlottesville, on May 9, 1952.
    The Hammer Bibliography, 1930-1952
    by Carolyn Reading, originally appended to the paper, has been published by the University of Kentucky Library." The title-page exists in two states: with the text 16 mm. from the top of the page (and 29 mm. from the bottom) and 30 mm. from the top (15 mm. from bottom).
  - Harding, Walter. A Centennial Check-List of the Editions of Henry David Thoreau's Walden. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press for Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1954. xxxii pp., 1954.3
    Plain brown dust jacket. "Two hundred and fifty copies of this checklist have been run on good paper and will be bound this fall [1953]. This will be sold by the University of Virginia Press at $2.50 per copy and will be available from them after January 1, 1954. Members of the Society are advised, however, that the bound edition on good paper is printed from the same type as the [free] advance sheets which they have received, and textually is no different" (
    29).
  - Mummendey, Richard. Language and Literature of the Anglo-Saxon Nations as Presented in German Doctoral Dissertations 1885-1950: A Bibliography / Die Sprache und Literatur der Angelsachsen in Spiegel der deutschen Universitatsschriften 1885-1950: Eine Bibliographie. (Bonner Beitrage zur Bibliotheks- und Bucherkunde, ed. Richard Mummendey, no. 1.) Bonn: H. Bouvier u. Co., Publishers; Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1954. xvi, 200 pp., 1954.4
    Stiff paper wrappers. 300 copies.
  - Quenzel, Carrol H. Edgar Snowden, Sr.: Virginia Journalist & Civic Leader. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1954. 59, [1] pp., 1954.5
    Stapled gatherings; no covering. "Offset from the author's [typescript] copy by The University Press under the supervision of Mark Rinker. Negatives by Conrad P. Poluito. Presswork by Poluito and Seward F. Stoneburner." The Special Collections Department of the University of Virginia Library has a copy with half-title (a blank page in other copies) and title page both reading "Edgar Snowden, Jr."; a note by John Cook Wyllie identifies this state as erroneous and this copy as one of three to have survived.
  - Alden, John. Bibliographica Hibernica: Additions and Corrections to Wing. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1955. 39, [1] pp., 1955.1
    Stapled gatherings; no covering. "Typed from author's copy by Sarah D. Spangler. Five hundred copies offset on an ATF Chief at the University of Virginia Press under the supervision of Charles E. Moran, Jr., by Conrad Poluito, for members of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia."
  - Knapp, Mary E. A Checklist of Verse by David Garrick. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press for Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1955. 69, [2] pp., 1955.2
    Slip "Errata & c." listing ten items laid in. "Advance [unbound] copies have been distributed without charge to the members of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia. In addition to these advance sheets, 250 copies have been printed and bound." 230 copies.
  - Morrison, Paul G. Index of Printers, Publishers, and Booksellers in Donald Wing's Short-Title Catalogue of Books Printed in England, Scotland, Ireland, Wales, and British America and of English Books Printed in Other Countries 1641-1700. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press for Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1955. 217, [2] pp., 1955.3
    Glassine dust jacket. "On the assumption that all buyers of the Wing Catalogue will not need the Index, two-thirds as many copies have been produced as were printed of the Wing Catalogue itself. Publication of the Index has proceeded with the knowledge and consent of the author, the sponsor, and the publisher of the original catalogue, who did not wish to undertake the Index. The work has been printed at the University of Virginia Press under the superintendence of Charles E. Moran, Jr. The type was set by Jerold M. Grizzle and Walter M. Collins; make-up was by Arthur B. Schmaling; forms were laid and locked up by Joseph B. Poindexter; presswork by William R. Travis; binding by Bohn of New York. The entire job was supervised by Mark Rinker." 920 copies.
  - O'Neal, William B. Jefferson's Fine Arts Library for the University for Virginia with Additional Notes on Architectural Volumes Known to Have Been Owned by Jefferson. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1956. [2], 53 pp., 1956.1
    "Issued on behalf of the Alderman Library and the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, [advance copies of] this study... [have] been distributed without charge to patrons of the library and to members of the Society."
  - Todd, William B. A Prospect of Society by Oliver Goldsmith Reconstructed from the Earliest Version of The Traveller by William B. Todd. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1956. [6], 30, [3] pp., 1956.2
    "All rights reserved | 1956 | Bibliographical Society of the | University of Virginia". "One hundred and fifty copies have been printed, of which one hundred are for sale at the University of Virginia Press." "This little book reproduces the edition of
    A Prospect of Society
    privately issued by the Water Lane Press in 1954 and the related article on the printing of the poem subsequently published in the 1955 volume of
    . "
  - Turnbull, Robert J. Bibliography of South Carolina 1563- 1950. With Explanatory Note by John Cook Wyllie and Foreword by Stuart W. Jackson. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1956. 5 vols. xii, [4], 504; [6], 504; [6], 504; [6], 504; [6], 552 pp., 1956.3
    Index published in 1960 as Vol. 6. Plain brown dust jackets. "All rights reserved | Bibliographical Society | University of Virginia | 1956". "The work is produced here as an uncorrected typist's copy posthumously made from an author's uncompleted handwritten manuscript. This explains both the present format and the reason for the limited and therefore costly edition. Variations in the intensity of the offset image are the direct result of copy photographed from typing that was not originally intended for photographic use." In a letter to the head of the University of South Carolina Press on 13 August 1973, the University Press of Virginia director Walker Cowen wrote, "I believe 250 sets were printed, but only about half that number bound. These were sold out very quickly, and, due to a confusion, the remaining sheets were destroyed before they could be put on the market."
  - Bowyer, T. H. A Bibliographical Examination of the Earliest Editions of the Letters of Junius. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1957. xxxiv, 147 pp., 1957.1
    Hardcover; also stapled gatherings, no covering. "All rights reserved | 1957 | Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia | 250 copies printed at the University of Virginia Press".
  - Harding, Walter. Thoreau's Library. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1957. [2], 102 pp., 1957.2
    "Copyright 1957 | The University of Virginia | Published jointly by the Thoreau Society and the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia. Unbound copies have been distributed to the members of the two societies and 100 bound copies are for sale at $3.50 each." The half-title in copies distributed to the Thoreau Society reads "Thoreau Society Booklet Number Eleven," while in Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia copies it is "Thoreau's Library."
  - Hirsch, Rudolph, Howell J. Heaney, Fredson Bowers, and Lucy Clark. Selective Check Lists of Bibliographical Scholarship, 1949- 1955. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1957. viii, 192 pp., 1957.3
    Separate issue, in red boards, of Vol. 10 ("Decennial Extra Volume"; blue boards) of
    .
  - James Branch Cabell: A Bibliography. Vol. 1: James Branch Cabell: A Bibliography of His Writings, Biography and Criticism, by Frances Joan Brewer. With a Foreword by James Branch Cabell. [2], 206 pp. Vol. 2: James Branch Cabell: A Bibliography, Part II. Notes on the Cabell Collections at the University of Virginia, by Matthew J. Bruccoli. 178 pp. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1957., 1957.4
    "All Rights Reserved | Bibliographical Society of the | University of Virginia | 1957".
  - Alden, John. The Muses Mourn: A Checklist of Verse Occasioned by the Death of Charles II. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1958. 61, [1] pp., 1958.1
    Glassine dust jacket.
  - Alden, John. Wing Addenda and Corrigenda: Some Notes on Materials in the British Museum. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1958. 19 pp., 1958.2
    Mimeographed; stiff paper covers, with tape spine.
  - Cox, Martha. Maxwell Anderson Bibliography. Charlottesville: USUVa, 1958. [8], 117, [2] pp., 1958.3
  - Flasche, Hans. Romance Languages and Literatures as Presented in German Doctoral Dissertations 1885-1950: A Bibliography / Die Sprachen und Literaturen der Romanen im Spiegel der deutschen Universitatsschriften: Eine Bibliographie / Langues et litteratures romanes dans les publications universitaires allemandes 1885-1950: une bibliographie. (Bonner Beitrage zur Bibliotheks- und Bucherkunde, ed. Richard Mummendey, no. 3.) Bonn: H. Bouvier u. Co., Publishers; Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1958. xxii, 299, [1] pp., 1958.4
    400 copies.
  - Kerlan, Irvin. A Roger Duvoisin Bibliography. Secretary's News Sheet 39 (March 1958)., 1958.5
  - Lester, John A., Jr. John Davidson: A Grub Street Bibliography. Secretary's News Sheet 40 (September 1958)., 1958.6
  - Fink, Frances Sharf. Heads Across the Sea: An Album of Eighteenth- Century English Literary Portraits in America. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, distributed by University of Virginia Press, 1959. [16], [44 pp. illus.], 251 pp., 1959.1
    Glassine dust jacket. 753 copies.
  - Kane, Mary. A Bibliography of the Works of Fiske Kimball, ed. Frederick Doveton Nichols. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1959. [8], 67 pp., 1959.2
    Glassine dust jacket. "Published jointly by | The Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia | The American Association of Architectural Bibliographers | The Society of Architectural Historians." 468 copies.
  - Meyen, Fritz. The North European Nations as Presented in German University Publications 1885-1957: A Bibliography / Die nordeuropaischen Lander im Spiegel der deutschen Universitatsschriften 1885-1957: Eine Bibliographie. (Bonner Beitrage zur Bibliotheks- und Bucherkunde, ed. Richard Mummendey, no. 4.) Bonn: H. Bouvier u. Co., Publishers; Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1959. xxi, [1], 124, [2] pp., 1959.3
  - O'Neal, William B. A Checklist of Writings on Thomas Jefferson as an Architect. Secretary's News Sheet 43 (September 1959)., 1959.4
  - Spoerri, James F. James Joyce: Books and Pamphlets Relating to the Author and His Works. Secretary's News Sheet 42 (August 1959)., 1959.5
  - De Bellis, Jack. An Andrew Nelson Lytle Check List. Secretary's News Sheet 46 (June 1960)., 1960.1
  - Evans, G. Blakemore, ed. Shakespearean Prompt-Books of the Seventeenth Century. Vol. I, Part i: General Introduction; Introduction to the Padua Macbeth; Collations. Part ii: Text of the Padua Macbeth. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1960. [6], 39; [24] pp., 1960.2
    Parts in stiff paper wrappers, together in portfolio within slipcase. "The Padua
    Macbeth
    prompt-book forms the first volume in a series of seventeenth-century Shakespearean prompt-books to be published under the auspices of the Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia. The prompt-book is reproduced in collotype facsimile (reduced in size by 10 per cent), accompanied by a critical Introduction and a complete collation and description of all cuts, changes, prompt-calls, property notes, etc. and a detailed comparison of these with later seventeenth-and eighteenth-century acting versions. A General Introduction to the whole series prefaces this first volume." "Part ii of the Padua
    was printed by The Meriden Gravure Company under the supervision of E. Harold Hugo on Arches heavyweight laid ivory paper. The title page, its verso, the captions and the colophon were printed letterpress and the pages of the First Folio were reproduced by collotype." For subsequent volumes in the series see 1963.2, 1964.3, 1966.3, 1970.3, 1980.1, 1989.1, 1996.1; for electronic edition see 1997.2.
  - Gross, Seymour L. Eudora Welty: A Bibliography of Criticism and Comment. Secretary's News Sheet 45 (April 1960)., 1960.3
  - Kaufman, Paul. Borrowings from the Bristol Library 1773- 1784. Charlottesville: Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia, 1960. [2], 138 pp., 1960.4
  - Turnbull, Robert J. Bibliography of South Carolina 1563- 1950. Vol. 6: Index, by Anne Freudenberg. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, 1960. viii, [4], 147 pp., 1960.5
    Plain brown dust jacket. "This index undertakes two things. It serves as a complete guide to the authors and titles in the five volumes of Robert J. Turnbull's
    Bibliography of South Carolina
    [1956].... In addition, a comprehensive subject index to Volume I was attempted." 279 copies.
  - Verner, Coolie. A Carto-Bibliographical Study of The English Pilot The Fourth Book with Special Reference to the Charts of Virginia. Charlottesville: University of Virginia Press, [1960]. viii, 87, [1] pp., 1960.6
    Glassine dust jacket. "Copyright 1960 | Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia".